how does a concussion actually work to
zoom out for a second I think one of the
reasons why we have really failed to
produce consistent therapies or
reproducible therapies for concussions
is because we don't study them properly
and we don't stud them properly because
we don't understand them properly hard
to fix when you can't Define exactly and
so what is normally done or when people
think about a concussion and if you read
papers you'll still see this um
consistently experts in the field
talking about
it you you'll hear something like the
slush effect um or you know you imagine
a head getting bashed and then like the
brain banging around inside the skull
like hitting one side of hitting one
side of the skull then banging and
hitting the other side that's what they
call a contra injury which is basically
you see some injury on the opposite side
from from where the impact
occurred the brain is
you know it's mainly fat and water and
it is then surrounded by fluid and it's
inside uh Solid box and that fluid is
full of salt that fluid is full of
salt if you take a solid box full of
water even if it's got something very
fragile inside and you shake it really
hard that fragile thing does not bang
against the sides because the water is
Right buffers it or the you know the CSF
the fluid I saw you do this it was the
one of the coolest things I've ever seen
you took an egg and you put it in a jar
with salt water I don't remember the
concentration you put it in it was just
like normal yeah normal sighting yeah
and you you know screwed the top of a
ball jar or whatever it was and you
shook the living crap out of the egg and
the yolk didn't break yeah at all no cuz
it's not hitting anything no it's
smashed it stays right in the it stays
right in the middle I in that moment I
went I what like everything cuz I had
said that always I did not know that
until you showed me that yeah not me but
you're were showing other people and I
was like wow so if if you could while
I'm shaking it image the jar what you
would see is you would see
distortions um along the surface of the
egg yolk inside inside this jar so there
are distortions so the egg instead of
being a perfect circle turns into an
oval it's not smashing against the wall
it's just being distorted and it's being
um accordioned exactly squished and and
pulled back apart right so how we
generally study can s is the other
version of of the egg experiment which I
also showed which is that you have your
your egg yolk in your solution and you
leave a big chunk of air in the top of
the jar you shake that immediately it
turns into salad dressing right
immediately you dispers that egg yolk
throughout the liquid that's how we
normally study concussion but what
happens um if you then look at where
injury is in people who've had
concussions so like you look at
individuals who have uh CTE right they
probably have some ongoing history of
concussions it's happened multiple times
if you look at where the injury has
accumulated it's not at the surface of
of the brain it's not the brain banging
against the skull what's happening is
that these distortions like waves of
energy that are transferred through the
brain is are the interfaces of different
parts of the brain so particularly the
interfaces between the gray matter on
the outside and the white matter
underneath it's connective tissue yeah
they're tearing the connective yeah so
right at the usually right the the base
of the sulai so you think about the
brain is really wrinkly right those are
the gy the the sort of the divots in
between those wrinkles the sulai at the
base of those that's where you tend to
see uh injury and it's because you have
uh tissues of different densities where
then the Distortion travels at different
rates so then you create this shearing
effect at those interfaces and then
that's right and if the shearing effect
is very large you can rip axons you so
create direct direct axonal injury um if
it's a blast wave then obviously you're
not directly shearing anything but you
still you still seem to injure those
same areas because the energy wave is
transferring through the brain at at
different rates and so that's where the
injury accumulates is at TH at those
interfaces so then how do things like
creatine and lactate help do they work
at all and if so how I've been uh really
excited about the potential for lactate
in traumatic brain injury and and that
uh excitement aligns very similarly to
with ketones
um but people have been talking about
them for a long time and I'm still
waiting for some good some good human
studies I've been probably talking about
it for a decade online like in front of
people on podcasts and things like that
yeah so I I believe that they could be
beneficial but we just haven't seen
really high quality evidence yet however
now that's clear we haven't seen
evidence that shows they don't work
either no the stud aren't being done no
no and if if I were to get a significant
concussion or TBR
like I'm going straight to the keton
Esters because I believe that there's a
high chance of benefit with low risk
anybody who's like I don't have a
randomized control trial to tell you
that that's the case but you know I
think it could if it was my brain that's
what I would do as an mdphd in brain
health this is what you would do infer
that for what you will folks uh part of
it is that it's essentially providing
some kind of metabolic substrate in an
area of the brain where there is
impaired metabolism so one of the
consistent responses you see to an
accute brain injury and again Strokes
cardiac arrests traumatic brain injuries
is what we call Energy failure so
there's this uh gap between energy
requirements and energy Supply because
you have dysfunctional
mitochondria ketones and lactate can
kind of bypass some of that and seem to
be
um less uh less energy energetically
expensive or they're more energetically
efficient in terms of generating ATP
like the effect is small but in that
kind of setting a small effect uh may
you know may be enough to help to help
minimize injury there's also going to be
some other signaling effects that that
could that could be beneficial um like
both lactate and ketones have a whole
range of other um anti-inflammatory um
neurotrophic kind of effects so so
lactates seems to help and ketones seem
to help drive an increase in production
in bdnf brain derive neurotrophic factor
which could help uh recovery so beyond
their effect on um your metabolism they
may have these other Downstream uh
effects as well but another reason why
this is important is that in the acute
uh injury setting the brain may become
relatively uh insensitive to glucose or
glucose uptake decreases so um but that
doesn't seem to be the case because the
the transport is different and both
ketones and lactate go in through the
monoc carboxilate Transporters which
aren't necessarily affected in that
state so some of it could be that
particularly ketones might be more um
metabolically efficient in terms of
energy production but also they're may
be more likely to get into the brain in
the setting of of an acute injury to
help support are they potentially less
negatively influenced by inflammatory
markers as well um yes potentially
although I mean it kind of depends on
what's what's going on on how they're
getting in if you enjoyed this clip you
can watch the full episode by clicking
here